Guide to the Kenneth Scott Latourette Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Kenneth Scott Latourette Papers
1905-1970
RG 3
Yale University Divinity School Library
70
(169 boxes)
The papers contain extensive documentation of Latourette's personal life, scholarly activities, and involvement in various organizations. Latourette was a professor of missions and Oriental history at Yale University. He held leadership positions in the American Baptist Convention and Foreign Mission Society, American Historical Association, Far Eastern Association, International Committee of Y.M.C.A.'s, Japan International Christian University Foundation, United Board for Christian Colleges in China, World Council of Churches, and Yale-China Association.
Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1884-1968
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kenneth Scott Latourette
Biographical / Historical
1884 Aug 6 Born in Oregon City, Oregon, son of DeWitt Clinton and Rhoda (Scott) Latourette
1904 B.S., Linfield College, McMinnville, Oregon
1906 B.A., Yale
1909 Ph.D., Yale
1909-1910 Traveling secretary, Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions
1910-1912 Faculty member, College of Yale in China, Changsha, China (forced to return for health reasons)
1914-1916 Prof. of history, Reed College, Portland, Oregon
1916-1921 Prof. of history, Denison University, Granville, Ohio
1918 Ordained to the Baptist ministry
1921 -1927 Prof. of missions, Yale
1927-1953 Prof. of missions and Oriental history
1938 Received Order of Jade from Chinese government
1938-1946 Chairman, Department of Religion, Graduate School, Yale
1946-1953 Director of Graduate Studies, Department of Religion, Yale
1953-1968 Prof. Emeritus, Yale
1968 Dec 26 Died in Oregon City, Oregon
Latourette held leadership positions in the following organizations:
American Baptist Convention and Foreign Mission Society
American Historical Association
Far Eastern Association
International Board, Y.M.C.A.
Japan International Christian University Foundation
United Board for Christian Colleges in China
World Council of Churches
Yale-in-China Association
Scope and Contents
The papers are arranged in five series:
I. Correspondence and Collected Material
II.Diaries and Ledgers
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
IV. Writings, Addresses, Notes (1974)
V. Writings, Addresses, Notes (1983)
The papers contain extensive documentation of Latourette's personal life, scholarly activities, and involvement in various organizations. The material organized in 1974 is given minimal description in this register. The material added in 1983, has been processed according to current YDSL standards and is described in more detail.
The first series, Correspondence, is divided into three Sections: Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, and Postcards. The Family Correspondence section contains letters to and from Latourette's more immediate relations. There are various letters addressed to "Uncle Ken" in the General Correspondence section because of that term's common usage among Latourette's students. The General Correspondence documents the full range of Latourette's involvements. A list of prominent correspondents is contained in the first folder of this series. Two bound volumes of letters written to Latourette by his colleagues at the time of his retirement are located in the oversize box of Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series III.
Material added to Series I in 1983 includes letters and papers related to Latourette's involvement in various organizations and projects. Latourette was, for example, Chairman of the Committee on Research of the International Missionary Council and in that capacity sought to assemble every few years a list of unpublished studies on missions topics. The material filed under International Missionary Council in Series I includes letters to and/or from prominent individuals in the field of missions such as Henrik Kraemer, John R. Mott, Julius Richter, D. M. Schlunk, Bengt Sundkler, and A. L. Warnshuis. Correspondence and papers filed under the Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America contain interesting material related to a statement by Latourette about the "Cairo Communique" of December 1943 and subsequent responses.
The second series, Diaries and Ledgers, contain five diaries from the years 1905 to 1916 and two ledgers from the years 1917 to 1921 and 1922 to 1924. Latourette's experiences as a faculty member of Yale-in-China, 1910-1912, are documented in the diaries.
Series III, Personal Items and Memorabilia, contains photographs, degrees,citations, artifacts, and biographical documentation.
Series IV, Writings, Addresses, Notes, contains articles, book reviews, pamphlets, and papers by Latourette, reviews of Latourette's works, material related to his family, and manuscripts. Series V contains similar material that was added to the papers in 1983.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence and Collected Material
II.Diaries and Ledgers
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia
IV. Writings, Addresses, Notes
V. Writings, Addresses, Notes
Missions -- China; Missions; Authors; Clergy; Educators; Bates, M. Searle (Miner Searle), 1897-1978; Beach, Harlan P. (Harlan Page), 1854-1933; Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1884-1968; Mott, John R. (John Raleigh), 1865-1955; Porter, David R. (David Richard), 1882-1973; Van Dusen, Henry P. (Henry Pitney), 1897-1975; Weigle, Luther A. (Luther Allan), 1880-1976; American Baptist Foreign Mission Society; American Historical Association; Association for Asian Studies; Japan International Christian University Foundation, Inc; United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia; World Council of Churches; Yale-in-China Association; Young Men's Christian Associations of North America. International Committee
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided as follows:
  Family Correspondence: Most of the letters in this section were written or received by KSL but some were exchanged between other members of the family. Correspondence of Latourette family members is filed by its author's name. The few letters received from non-relations are filed according to recipient. The material within each folder is arranged chronologically. A variety of Latourette family material, including letters- dated 1861 to 1862 from Ezra Fisher and possibly his wife, and "Family History: A Sketch", written by KSL, are located at the end of this section.
  General Correspondence: The letters are arranged alphabetically by author, except for the few letters written by KSL, which are filed according to recipient. The material of denominations, conventions and local churches is frequently located under more than one heading. For example, correspondence related to local Baptist churches may be filed under "Baptist" or under the name of the city in which the church is located. It should be noted that Correspondence lacking a surname is filed by Christian name. Letters signed "John," for example, are filed in a folder labelled "J" at the beginning of the "J" correspondence. IIllegible signatures, anonymous letters, cards and fragments are filed at the end of the section. A list of lengthy or prominent correspondents is in the first folder.
  Postcards: The postcards are divided into two categories, those received by KSL and those received by his father. The postcards are arranged chronologically.
  Correspondence added in 1983.
  - Family Correspondence
    - Bradshaw - Eaton, Esther (Box 1)
    - Eaton, Lucy Ruth (Box 2–3)
    - Eaton, William - Hogg, Sarah Ann (Box 4)
    - Hogg, William Richey (Box 5)
    - Hogg, Wilma Ruth (Box 6)
    - Hollowell, Alan - Hollowell, Cathy (Box 7)
    - Hollowell, Dorothy Elizabeth (Box 8–9)
    - Hollowell, Homer - Latourette, John (Box 10)
    - Kenneth Scott Latourette to Lucy Ruth Eaton and Dorothy Elizabeth Hollowell (Box 11)
    - KSL to Dorothy Elizabeth Hollowell (Box 12–15)
    - KSL to Hollowell, Homer and Wilma Ruth Hogg (Box 16)
    - KSL to parents (Box 17–23)
    - Latourette, Lillie May - Latourette, Perrin (Box 24)
    - Latourette, Rhoda (Scott) (Box 25–28)
    - Llewellyn, Janet - Stewart, John D. (Box 29)
    - Stewart, Lucy Alfreda (Box 30–31)
    - Young, Maud; Family history materials, including early letters by Ezra Fisher and his wife. (Box 32)
  - General Correspondence - original sequence
    - A - Alldredge (Box 33)
    - Allen - American Baptist Convention (Box 34)
    - American Baptist Foreign Mission Board - American Bible Society (Box 35)
    - American Board - American Institute (Box 36)
    - American Journal - Arends (Box 37)
    - Arkansas - Ayers (Box 38)
    - B - Baptist Church (Box 39)
    - Baptist, Connecticut - Barton (Box 40)
    - Bass - Beech (Box 41)
    - Beeghly - Blake (Box 42)
    - Blakely - Breck (Box 43)
    - Breckinridge - Brushwyler (Box 44)
    - Brussels - Cahiers (Box 45)
    - Calder - Campbell (Box 46)
    - Campbell, Donald Kennedy II (Box 46A)
    - Canadian - Chadwick (Box 47)
    - Challenge - Chidley (Box 48)
    - Chih - Christianity (Box 49)
    - Chu - Cochrane (Box 50)
    - Cockayne - Community (Box 51)
    - Compton - Cortright (Box 52)
    - Cory - Culver (Box 53)
    - Cummings - Dawe (Box 54)
    - Dawley - Ditman (Box 55)
    - Ditmanson - Durgin (Box 56)
    - Durham - Ellis (Box 57)
    - Elmira - Exman (Box 58)
    - Eyre - Fellows (Box 59)
    - Fellowship - Ferger (Box 60)
    - Ferguson - Fong (Box 61)
    - Foochow - Franklin (Box 62)
    - Frazer - Gatewood (Box 63)
    - Gauger - Goodwin (Box 64)
    - Goold - Guenther (Box 65)
    - Guetzkow - Harcourt (Box 66)
    - Harde - Harper (Box 67)
    - Harpole - Hayes (Box 68)
    - Hayward - Hobson (Box 69)
    - Hocking - Houghton Mifflin Company (Box 70)
    - Houston - Hutchinson (Box 71)
    - Hutnek - International Mark (Box 72)
    - International Missionary Council (Box 73)
    - International Press - Jacoby (Box 74)
    - Jader - Jolley (Box 75)
    - Jones - Keithahn (Box 76)
    - Keller - Koinonia (Box 77)
    - Kokusai - Kuizenga (Box 78)
    - Kuling - Lawrence (Box 79)
    - Lawson - Lemon (Box 80)
    - Leng - Linfield College (Box 81)
    - Ling - Loverude (Box 82)
    - Lovett - McClelland (Box 83)
    - MacClennan - McKinley (Box 84)
    - McKinney - Macmillan Company (Box 85)
    - McMinnville - Marney (Box 86)
    - Marquis - Mendenhall (Box 87)
    - Meng - Millard's (Box 88)
    - Millegan - Minus (Box 89)
    - Mission - Morowich (Box 90)
    - Morpurgo - National Academy (Box 91)
    - National Association - Nettleton (Box 92)
    - Nevendorffer - Nolde (Box 93)
    - Nolen - Ogle (Box 94)
    - Ogren - Oxford (Box 95)
    - Oxnam - Payne (Box 96)
    - Peace - Pickens (Box 97)
    - Pickerings - Potter (Box 98)
    - Potts - Prior (Box 99)
    - Prichard - Ray (Box 100)
    - Read - Religion in Life (Box 101)
    - Religions - Robbins (Box 102)
    - Roberts - Round (Box 103)
    - Rouse - Ryter (Box 104)
    - S - Scholastic (Box 105)
    - Schoning - Sharman (Box 106)
    - Sharp - Simplified (Box 107)
    - Simpson - Smith, Lincoln (Box 108)
    - Smith, Lycius - Sorik (Box 109)
    - Sowards - Stein (Box 110)
    - Steinheimer - Student (Box 111)
    - Student Volunteer - Swilley (Box 112)
    - Swing - Thompson (Box 113)
    - Thomson - Trinity (Box 114)
    - Trotter - Union Medical (Box 115)
    - Union Theological - Vandenhoeck (Box 116)
    - Vander - Wales (Box 117)
    - Waleshouse - Weber (Box 118)
    - Webster - Whale (Box 119)
    - Wheaton - Willcox (Box 120)
    - Willeke - Wold (Box 121)
    - Wolf - World Council (Box 122)
    - World Dominion - Y (Box 123)
    - Yale-in-China (Box 124)
    - Yale University (Box 125)
    - Yale University (Box 126)
    - Yamada - YMCA (Box 127)
    - Younger - Z, Anonymous (incl. KSL to "Fellows" 1914-1918), Formerly restricted file of Foreign Missions Conference of N.A. correspondence regarding situation of church in Japan 1940-1943 (Box 128)
    - Re: Trips - Europe 1954, South America 1956 (Box 129)
    - Postcards (Box 130–132)
  - General Correspondence - addendum
    - American Bible Society, 1962-1966, n.d. (Box 162, Folder 1)
    - American Council of Learned Societies Committee on the Promotion of Chinese Studies (see also: Conference on Far Eastern Studies, 1928-1930 (Box 162, Folder 2 - 4)
    - American Oriental Society (see also: Conference on Far Eastern Studies, 1929-1936 (Box 162, Folder 5)
    - Calvin Theological Seminary, 1968 (Box 162, Folder 6)
    - China Medical Board, Inc., 1934-1945 (Box 162, Folder 7 - 13)
    - China Medical Board, Inc., 1946-1949 (Box 163, Folder 14 - 15)
    - Conference on Far Eastern Studies (see also: American Council of Learned Studies and American Oriental Society), 1929-1931 (Box 163, Folder 16 - 17)
    - Eastern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1968 (Box 163, Folder 18)
    - Far East Settlement Group (FCCCA and FMCNA), 1941-1944 (Box 163, Folder 19)
    - Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America- Commission to Study the Basis of a Just and Durable Peace, 1941-1944, n.d. (Box 163, Folder 20 - 24)
    - Foreign Missions Conference of North America re. conferences of Japanese and American leaders (See also formerly restricted file in Box 128), 1941 (Box 164, Folder 25)
    - International Missionary Council - Committee on Research, 1930-1936 (Box 164, Folder 26 - 37)
    - International Missionary Council - Committee on Research, 1937-1948, n.d. (Box 165, Folder 38 - 43)
    - Japan International Christian University Foundation, Inc., 1964-1968 (Box 165, Folder 44)
    - Joint Committee for the Study of Christian Unity (FCCCA and FMCNA), 1940-1941 (Box 165, Folder 45)
    - National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A., 1968 (Box 165, Folder 46)
    - Union Theological Seminary, 1956-1962 (Box 165, Folder 47)
    - World Conference on Faith and Order, 1940 (Box 165, Folder 48)
    - World Council of Churches - Committee on the History of the Ecumenical Movement - Correspondence, 1947-1951, n.d. (Box 165, Folder 49 - 50)
    - WCC - Committee on the History of the Ecumenical Movement - Memos and Minutes, 1947-1951 (Box 165, Folder 51 - 52)
    - WCC - Committee on the History of the Ecumenical Movement- Chapter outlines (Box 165, Folder 53)
    - WCC - Committee on the History of the Ecumenical Movement- comments on KSL chapter, 1948-1950 (Box 166, Folder 54)
    - WCC - re. process of formation, 1938, 1940 (Box 166, Folder 55)
    - WCC - Study Department, 1942, 1948 (Box 166, Folder 56)
    - World Dominion Movement, 1935-1939, n.d. (Box 166, Folder 57)
    - Yale-in-China, 1933 (Box 166, Folder 58)
    - Yale University - Committee on Far Eastern Studies, 1933-1946, n.d. (Box 166, Folder 59 - 63)
    - Yale University, Department of Religion - Committee on Graduate Studies, 1950-1951,n.d. (Box 166, Folder 64)
- Diaries and Ledgers, 1905-1924; Series II
  - Five diaries and two ledgers, 1905-1924 (Box 133)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series III
  - Biographical documentation, incl. articles about KSL, obituaries, and a bibliography of KSL works, 1938 - 1970, n.d. (Box 166, Folder 66 - 67)
  - Honorary degrees, incl. from the University of Wales, signed by Philip, Duke of Edinburgh; citations; photographs; silver plate from the American Baptist Convention; two bound volumes of letters to Kenneth Scott Latourette re: his retirement (1953); scrolls; sketch of Kenneth Scott Latourette in pen and ink; brass paper weight inscribed with a Confucian verse (Box OV1)
  - Photographs, honorary degrees, gavels, etc. (Box 134–135)
  - Photographs - portraits of Latourette, 1923-1948, no date (Box 169, Folder 89)
  - Photographs of others: A - T (Box 169, Folder 90-95)
  - Photographs of others: V - Y and unidentified (Box 170, Folder 96)
  - Photographs: groups, including Latourette (Box 170, Folder 97)
  - Photographs: groups, miscellaneous (Box 170, Folder 98)
  - Photographs: places - Latourette's room (Box 170, Folder 99)
  - Photographs: places - miscellaneous (Box 171)
- Writings, Clippings, Notes - Original sequence, Series IV
  The original sequence of writings, clippings, and notes is divided into the following subsections:
  A. Articles by KSL: arranged alphabetically by title
  B. Book reviews by KSL: arranged alphabetically according to author
  C. Reviews of KSL's books: arranged chronologically
  D. Clippings related to family and general matters: arranged chronologically
  E. Articles, pamphlets, manuscripts by KSL: arranged chronologically
  F. Papers by KSL: arranged chronologically
  G. Notes for lectures, talks, and sermons: arranged topically
  - Articles by KSL
    - By title (Box 136–138)
  - Book reviews by KSL
    - Of works by Abbott - Holcombe (Box 139)
    - Of works by Holland - Richards (Box 140)
    - Of works by Richardson - Wu, plus misc. review published in YDN (Box 141)
  - Reviews of KSL's books
    - Reviews (Box 142–144)
  - Clippings
    - Clippings (Box 145)
  - Articles, pamphlets, manuscripts
    - Articles, pamphlets, manuscripts, 1933-1942 (Box 146)
    - Articles, pamphlets, manuscripts, 1943-1952 (Box 147)
    - Articles, pamphlets, manuscripts, 1953-1961 (Box 148)
    - Articles, pamphlets, manuscripts, 1962-1968 (Box 149)
  - Papers by KSL
    - Papers (Box 150)
  - Notes for lectures, talks, and sermons
    - Miscellaneous (Box 150A)
- Manuscripts, Series V
  This series is divided into two subsections: Lengthy manuscripts, and Brief or incomplete manuscripts
  - Lengthy manuscripts
    - "A Short History of Christianity": Chapters 1 - 47 (Box 151)
    - "A Short History of Christianity": Chapters 48 - 61 (Box 152)
    - "A Short History of Christianity": Chapters 1 - 38 (Box 153)
    - "The Chinese: Their History and Culture" (2 drafts) (Box 154)
    - "History of the Expansion of Christianity" (partial) (Box 155)
    - "Challenge to Protestants" (2 drafts) (Box 156)
    - "Christianity in a Revolutionary Age: the 19th Century in Europe" (Box 157)
    - "A History of the American Bible Society, 1816-1966" (Box 157)
  - Brief or incomplete manuscripts
    - Various (Box 158–160)
- Writings - Addendum, Series VI
  The writings addendum is divided into three subsections:
  A. Addresses, interviews, notes
  B. Manuscripts: arranged alphabetically by title with dates noted as available
  C. Published writings: arranged chronologically
  - Addresses, interviews, notes
    - Various, 1952-1962, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 65-67)
  - Manuscripts
    - American Presbyterianism Serving Overseas, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 69)
    - Buddhism: A Comprehensive Sketch, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 69)
    - A Call to Mission and Unity (Box 167, Folder 70)
    - The China That Is To Be (Condon Lectures), 1949 (Box 167, Folder 70)
    - The Christian College and University: Why and What is it? (Box 167, Folder 70)
    - The Christian Future, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 70)
    - The Christian Scriptures and the Religious Classics of the Orient (Box 167, Folder 71)
    - The Christian Understanding of History (Box 167, Folder 71)
    - Data on the Distribution of the Missionary Enterprise: Changes in Three Decades, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 72)
    - Discussion Materials by KSL, Theme for the Month: What is the World Mission of the Church?, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 72)
    - Ecumenical Bearings of the Missionary Movement and the International Missionary Council (Chapter for History of the Ecumenical Movement, edited by R. Rouse and S.C. Neill) (Box 167, Folder 73)
    - Foreword to Dr. Norman Goodall's History of the London Missionary Society After 1895 (Box 167, Folder 74)
    - A Historian Looks Ahead: The Future of Christianity in the Light of its Past, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 74)
    - The Historical Background of Church and Community, 1936 (Box 167, Folder 74)
    - The Laymen's Foreign Missions Inquiry: The Report of its Commission of Appraisal, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 75)
    - List of unpublished studies dealing with religions and the spread of Christianity, 1931 (Box 167, Folder 75)
    - The Philosophy of Christian Education, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 75)
    - The Place of the Missionary in the World Church, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 75)
    - The Present Status of Foreign Missions, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 76)
    - Problems Confronting Christian Missions in the Far East, n.d. (Box 167, Folder 76)
    - Protestant Higher Education in China: An Historical Sketch and Appraisal (Box 167, Folder 76)
    - The Recognition of Missions by Our College and Seminary Curriculums (Box 167, Folder 77)
    - The Relation of Christian Faith to History and the Social Sciences (Box 167, Folder 77)
    - The Relation of the church and the Environment, 1940 (Box 167, Folder 77)
    - La Religion del Periodo Colonial y su Aportacion a los Ideales y la Vida de los Estados Unidos (Box 167, Folder 77)
    - Research and Christian Missions, 1932 (Box 167, Folder 77)
    - The Share of American Baptists in the World Mission of the Church, n.d. (Box 168, Folder 78)
    - Theological Education and the World-Wide Church (Box 168, Folder 78)
    - This I Believe, n.d. (Box 168, Folder 78)
    - The Twilight of a Great Era: Darkness or Dawn?, n.d. (Box 168, Folder 79)
    - What Can We Expect in the World Missions?, n.d. (Box 168, Folder 79)
  - Published Writings
    - "The History of the Far East, a Neglected Field" in The History Teacher's Magazine, 1916 (Box 168, Folder 80)
    - "The History of Early Relations Between the United States and China, 1784-1844" in Transactions of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, Vol. XXII, 1917 (Box 168, Folder 88)
    - "China, the United States and the War" in The League of Nations, 1919 (Box 168, Folder 80)
    - "Japan and Christian Missionaries to China" in The Chinese Recorder, 1919 (Box 168, Folder 80)
    - "Chinese Historical Studies During the Past Seven Years" in American Historical Review, 1921 (Box 168, Folder 80)
    - "China Under the Republic" in Institute of International Education, 1921 (Box 168, Folder 80)
    - "The Proving of Isabel M. Grover" in Linfield College Bulletin Supplement, 1922 (Box 168, Folder 81)
    - "Impressions of Some Present Tendencies in the Christian Movement in China" in The Chinese Recorder, 1922 (Box 168, Folder 81)
    - "Roman Catholic and Protestant Misisons in China: Some Comparisons" in The International Review of Misisons, 1926 (Box 168, Folder 81)
    - "Boards and Missionaries: Suggestions Toward an Understanding" in The Chinese Recorder, 1927 (Box 168, Folder 81)
    - "Voyages of American Ships to China, 1784-1844" in Transactions of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1927 (Box 168, Folder 81)
    - "A Missionary's Relation with Fellow-Westerners" in The Student Volunteer Movement Bulletin, 1927 (Box 168, Folder 81)
    - "What Must We Do if our Christian Colleges are to be Christian?" in Christian Education, 1927 (Box 168, Folder 81)
    - "An Appreciation of Non-Christian Faiths" in The World Tomorrow, 1928 (Box 168, Folder 82)
    - "On Keeping Intellectually Alert" in The Student Volunteer Movement Bulletin, 1928 (Box 168, Folder 82)
    - "Far Eastern History in the World History Course in High School" in The Historical Outlook, 1929 (Box 168, Folder 82)
    - "Christian Missions in China", 1929 (Box 168, Folder 82)
    - "The Lamen's Foreign Missions Inquiry: The Report of its Commission of Appraisal" in The International Review of Misisons, 1933 (Box 168, Folder 82)
    - "Japan: Suggested Outlines for a Discussion of Japan, her History, Culture, Problems, and Relations with the United States" in Japan Society Syllabus, 1934 (Box 168, Folder 82)
    - "The Decisive Question Before Protestant Missions" in The Chinese Recorder, 1935 (Box 168, Folder 82)
    - "The Christian Association and the Foreign Missionary Enterprise" in Some Annals of the Yale Christian Association, 1937 (Box 168, Folder 83)